A Guide to the Papers of Henry James, 1855-1969, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
  - Two Men: A Novel by Elizabeth Stoddard by Henry James 1865, AMs, 23 pp. on 23 l. (Box-folder 1:17)
    - Henry James to "Dearest old Friends" [Mr. and Mrs. Daniel Sargent Curtis], 1907 May 24, ALS, 8 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 6:22)
      Coming to Rome again at end of week; spent three days at Turin after ten weeks in Paris. Will be at Vallombrosa with Ned Bait, then 3-5 days in Florence. Not every prospect pleases him in Italy now, but it is at him as much as ever. However, it's "at" Venice that he really wants to be, at dear old Barbaro and "them." They are the last refuge of peace amid desolation. #6251-ag
    - Henry James to "My dear patient Friends" [Mr. and Mrs. Daniel Sargent Curtis], 1907 June 6, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with typed transcript. (Box-folder 6:23)
      His departure from Rome suffers from his motoring with Filippos de Felippis to Naples. Leaves 11th for Florence, then will fly to them. #6251-ag
    - Henry James to [Douglas] Ainslie, 1907 June 9, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 6:24)
      Alas, he is far away, if you can say "alas" in front of the Bay of Naples on a lovely fresh June day. His invitation reaches him here. Would have come with pleasure had he been in London. Have been abroad nearly four months, and the end is not yet. Hopes to reach home again by the last days of this month and will come then. #6251-bd
    - Henry James to "My dear Friends" [Mr. and Mrs. Daniel Sargent Curtis], 1907 June 16, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 6:25)
      Returns from divinely beautiful place: the most beautiful he ever was in, and then shall start for Venice. Longs for splash of Adriatic against their cool water steps. They can have him for a week. He is impatient by waiting. #6251-ag
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Humphrey] Ward, 1907 June 22, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 6:26)
      How kind her excellent words regarding The American Scene. Loves to know book touched in her a chord of interest. It was a difficult job to do, and a projected sequel proved so difficult he has given it up altogether. Coming abroad for so many weeks in Paris, Rome, etc. doesn't make for the retention of American impressions. However, he is facing homeward impatiently. He is never in his life coming abroad again. She alludes to matters of which he wants to hear everything, and he shall knock at her door if she is enjoying the terrible London of June. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. Fletcher, 1907 June 23, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 6:27)
      His retarded, shrunken visit is over, and had difficulty taking place at all. Delighted to come to lunch Wednesday, the 26th. Wants all news of H.F. she can give him. #6251-ai
    - H[enry] J[ames] to Hendrik [Christian Anderson], 1907 July 18, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 6:28)
      Delayed thanking him for letter and photos. They all make those romantic Roman days live again. Vulgar world that's not Italy seized him again. Can't believe all the slowly breaking bust, the wild sessions at Aragno's, the wondrous terrace dinner of the last night, etc. were only last month. Never had coming back seemed so flat and common and humiliating. Hopes summer is melting his pains and disabilities away. #6251
    - Henry James to Alvin [Langdon Coburn], 1907 July 28, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 6:29)
      Rejoices in his return; too busy to write. Up for night in town on July 31st and will meet him then. #6251-g
    - Henry James to Violet [Hunt], 1907 August 28, ALS, 6 pp. on 3 l.; with typed transcript by Violet Hunt. (Box-folder 6:30)
      He has failed in the most comprehensive matter to keep in touch with for months. Doesn't do anything he needs to. Make plans, etc. as he did before years of infirmities had imposed on him the economics of existence which led him to make so poor a figure to her. Fevered London clashes were made up of appointments, etc. Has become too much and too many for him so he couldn't see her at all because of her social character. She is Society. Ancient quiet of his place is thing of the past: too many visitors. She must come down some autumn Sunday. #6251-o
    - Henry James to Clare [Frewen], 1907 October 8, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 6:31)
      How can she say the light of literature abandoned their province, when she herself sheds such charming letters. Sorry he was away when she came, as he could have put her up; hadn't meant to be away. Will never do it again. Make him another early sign and follow up on it. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Violet [Hunt], 1907 October 13, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l.; with typed transcript by Violet Hunt. (Box-folder 6:32)
      Hope she is in same good disposition, and will come to him for the weekend. Will she come 19th, 26th, or November 2? He shall be alone. #6251-o
    - Henry James to Violet [Hunt], 1907 October 31, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l.; with typed transcript by Violet Hunt. (Box-folder 6:33)
      Shall be at station Saturday at 6:30. He prays for a civil sun. What news of life she is depended on to bring. #6251-o
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Ada] Leverson, 1907 December 19, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 6:34)
      Jocelyn Perese brought James her kind letter, which has left him almost buried beneath mass of its liberality. Finds her a penetrating and generous reader and much touched by her appreciation of his style. James's people are all dead to him after their getting born. Compliments to J. Perese. #6251-r
    - Henry James to Bill [William James, Jr.], [1907] "Tuesday,", ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 6:35)
      All thanks and blessings. I return everything, with one rather painful (saddening) one from your Uncle Bob: his daughters' engagement by such perversity and insanity! Don't return to me, and don't keep this last. I send a letter of Peggy's; it is very interesting and delightful. James only a little disconcerted at his spoken to his family about returning home. Don't, oh Billy, don't! You give James such a turn. It knocks the fond dream he has of going over to see him, which won't be conveniently possible for him till February. Don't make any such projects. It's a great deal better to leave them to themselves for the winter. That is what they are adjusted to. But forgive their outbreak. J. S. Perry's visit was very pleasant, and gathers for him. Extraordinary mildness, if not hotness, right now. Don't desert your fond old Uncle. #6251-av
    - Henry James to [Edith] Sichel, 1908 January 14, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 6:36)
      She appeals to him in name of cherished memories and she sets insidious machinery at work. He hasn't habits or traditions of presiding at anything or introducing anyone, but will face the agony or risk the disgrace, all for the sake of introducing Andre Beaumier at his second conference. Give his love to the inestimable Anne Ritchie. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Hendrik [Christian Anderson], 1908 January 24, ALS, 6 pp. on 3 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 6:37)
      Horrible that his charming letter waited so long for an answer, but James has had a bad time; so much work holds him. Extreme pleasure to hear from him. News sounds good as he doesn't say he was unwell. Grand that things are okay. Holds his breath over the abundance of his inspiration; they will have to build a city to take his work in. James interested in the casting of his bust though scared he thinks him worthy. It will never do for it to be a gift, though his pocket has been empty of ready money. No chance to get bust exhibited in London as only British sculptors have that opportunity, but can exhibit privately. Cast it, photograph it, and send the picture to him, and he will work on getting it displayed. #6251
    - Henry James to Hendrik [Christian Anderson], 1908 February 9, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 6:38)
      Beautiful letter. Won't worry him with "value" question regarding bust, but rejoices in hearing of its bronze color. Preparing to receive it by building an altar to perch it on. #6251
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Humphrey] Ward, 1908 February 24, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 6:39)
      There is no London for him March 2. Besides which he had ceased to dine out forever and ever! Leaves him all the more disposable for tea. Can't be in town until April 1. On his return, he will come to tea every Thursday of the hereafter. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Violet [Hunt], 1908 April 1, ALS, 8 pp. on 2 l.; with typed transcript by Violet Hunt. (Box-folder 6:40)
      He has been horribly remiss, because he has been ridden for months by nightmare of an Edition Definitive, or pursued thereby by a pack of hell hounds. The volumes already out, revised, rewritten, etc. It has made him inhuman and remorseless. Then the production of the stage play in the provinces. Be sorry for him and patient; the play is a success in Edinburgh, so he may make the seven and nine pence which has been sordid motive for toil. Received her novel, but no time to read. When he reads critically he is a pig. Goes to Paris after Easter. #6251-o
    - Henry James to [Mr. and Mrs. Daniel Sargent Curtis], 1908 April 2, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 6:41)
      Touched by their good will towards his poor little stage, play stuff, only three acts and six characters. Did quite beautifully in Edinburgh and then Glasgow. Hopes it will come to London where it will have its chance. On his way back home for 2-3 weeks, then Paris for a fortnight, and May again in town. Met poor Alex Munthe in the street, and lunched with him and his wife, who is to have a baby; it makes the eyesight matter weigh light in the balance. #6251-ag
    - Henry James to C[hristopher] E. Wheeler, 1908 April 22, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. with typed transcript. (Box-folder 6:42)
      Going to Paris for 12-14 days, will send him tomorrow fresh copy of "The Saloon" embodying his effort to clarify crux of situation as much as he sees his way to, as yet. Done much to make his act go better, and space has been a blessing. Sends him copy and notes pages where there are changes. Will be in London May 10th for one month and will communicate with him from Reform Club. Wonders if H.G.B. is back and how affected and disposed he is. Taking conclusion of his New York question wholly for granted. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Hendrik [Christian Anderson], 1908 August 12, TLS, 2 pp. on 2 l. and ALS postscript, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 6:43)
      Reads his letter, and makes believe he dips into his life. Discusses The American, twice translated into German. P.S. Don't send letter on to Federn. #6251
    - Henry James to [Angelina] Milman, 1908 August 14, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 6:44)
      Greatly interested in her beautiful news, and touched by her impulse to communicate it to him herself. Very charming, wonderful, romantic, etc. What moves him to most enthusiasm is her projected flight to Zanzibar, but it is a superfluous and undesirable complication to a delightful occurrence. It was normal her marriage would bring her westward. He has pleasure of knowing Mr. [Edward W.] Clarke, having dined with him. Congratulates them both. She mustn't sneak away under pretext of Venice without his seeing her. Glad Venice still comes in for her. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. Henniker, 1908 August 16, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 6:45)
      Horrible he took so long to write; too many complications. Apologizes for being deaf to her appeal and tells her why. Sends check in attenuation of sorry case. It may still help to eke out something. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. Henniker, 1908 August 20, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with typed transcript. (Box-folder 6:46)
      All about a hopeless meeting. Hopes to conjure away blight by seeking her out in Stratford. In town only in snatches of time. Wishes E. Norris might be counted on for a little more of that. Deplored death of his remaining relations. He is a quiet obscure hero of patience and stoicism. He will never leave Torquay: there never was a less Londony man. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Humphrey] Ward, 1908 September 20, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 6:47)
      Charmed by beautiful regularity with which as she shakes the magic boughs, the fruits of her genius fall into his undeserving lap. Diana Mallory has just presented herself. She almost makes him feel as if he were the headlong reader of romance for which he has given up struggling to know himself. It's one hundred to one that she will presently work the miracle. He is sorrier than he can say for all the months that go by without their meeting. It would be in town as he goes nowhere else. Would go if he could find her at Grosvenor Place. Longs to see her. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Hendrik [Christian Anderson], 1908 September 22, TLS, 3 pp. on 3 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 6:48)
      Complicated season of the year with visits, family, etc. Writes about unknown Spanish artist Bacarisas who is coming to London for an exhibition. James sorry for Anderson, with Lincoln's indifference awaiting him. He will help, but has no contacts in art world: a great ferocious special region. Can't help with place to stay. #6251
    - Henry James to Alvin [Langdon Coburn], 1908 October 22, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 6:49)
      Wrong in thinking he did not see his exhibition. On the contrary, made use of his ticket. Admires his things: quality of his colorless work. Also drawn to his experiments in color, but not drawn to them yet. If he is going back to the United States don't cut his cables and stay, then they can talk. Doubts he will be in town before he sails. Probably will have another book to send before he goes; rest will wait his return. He is changing the set for him to the English issue. #6251-g
    - Henry James to Mrs. Henniker, 1908 November 11, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 6:50)
      Her note finds him in London, but leaves of necessity for home tomorrow, so no possibility of returning for many weeks. Regrets not seeing her or Rhoda [Broughton]. #6251-a
    - Henry James to [Lena Milman], 1908 November 11, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 6:51)
      Delighted to see her there on November 21st for luncheon. Sends cordial greetings to her "sposo" [Edward W. Clarke], not only for the small but for the whole long, or great, occasion to both of them. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Alvin [Langdon Coburn], 1908 December 8, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 6:52)
      Sorry not to answer his gentle note before he left London; he was occupied and tormented, and sorry to maltreat him. Hopes he survives all exposures, temptations, and tribulations. Since he couldn't send after extra volumes of editions, he won't have to cart them all over, and they will be there when he returns. Has received no American copies since June 12. Coburn probably having more lively appeals to his interest now. Hopes he is not doing so well that he won't be bettered by a fresh go at London. #6251-g
    - Henry James to Alvin [Langdon Coburn], 1908 December 19, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 6:53)
      Has written Scribner to communicate with him for one more frontispiece for another in extra volume of their edition. A New York subject is required, and he is there: story is Julia Bride. Get them to give him tale to read, and he will see what picture he may capture: some bit of the Park of the Metropolitan Museum. Do what he can. #6251-g
    - Henry James to Grace Carter, [1909 January 1], [1909 January 1], ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. with envelope and typed transcript. (Box-folder 6:54)
      Talks of using correspondence cards to write letters, and of sitting alone New Year's Day and remembering days gone by. Sorry to have missed her. Heard from the Benedicts that she is on the way to Cooperstown. She and the Benedicts have immortal youth, while he is rooted there. Come see him some day. #6251-ac
    - Henry James to Alvin [Langdon Coburn] 1909 January 22, TLS, 2 pp. on 2 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 6:55)
      Has two things from him: appeal for mention of his authorship of frontispieces, and his very suitable picture for extra volume. Shall commemorate him, appreciately, in last preface of the lot; that of The Golden Bowl. Couldn't have tackled business of the illustrations without him. Rejoices over news of Hammersmith residence. Do return with choices and charmingest horrors of New York; no one else will so appreciate or understand them. #6251-g
    - Henry James to [Mrs. Daniel Sargent Curtis] 1909 February 24, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 6:56)
      Kind of her to care for news of the small comedy of things, and to have taken pleasure in Jessie Allen's rosy report of it. It is a pot-boiler of 14-15 years ago, treacherously not done then by Ellen Terry for whom he wrote it. Disinterment after long years. It's his only little attempt to "write down" to the common intelligence of the awful London theatregoers. Can't think of Maud Story without anguish; what a tortured life! [John Singer] Sargent is doing magnificence for Boston; he has sold all of his watercolors to the Brooklyn Museum of Art. The Queen came to see him while James was there, looking a beautiful 30! #6251-ag
    - Henry James to Violet [Hunt], 1909 March 16, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with typed transcript by Violet Hunt. (Box-folder 6:57)
      She is not forgotten but he has had troubles and complications this winter. He has been depressingly unwell, though better now. Summer and autumn he swam in deep sea of family element. His pitch of life is lowered, which at his advanced age is an excellent thing. Think of him in a minor key. The Velvet Glove is the expiring kick. Shall come up to town for a month. The Dancing Girl a greater success than Henry Arthur's. #6251-o
    - Henry James to Violet [Hunt], 1909 April 6, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with typed transcript by Violet Hunt. (Box-folder 6:58)
      Will sign English Review that she may send, with pleasure. Is The Velvet Glove in the numbers? He is not eager for an overwhelming female electorate, and he doesn't see how any man in his senses can be. #6251-o
    - Henry James to R[obert] U[nderwood] Johnson, 1909 May 5, TLS, 4 pp on 3 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 6:59)
      Has an awful arrears of correspondence, which has snowed him in. Thanks for information on the next Ballot, but finds himself at a disadvantage for any sort of participation, so that he is tempted to ask him to not count him in at all. Confesses that he doesn't make out what we mean, or are, or intend or design or represent, what our organization is all about. The most recent document sent him was as vague and colorless and neutral to an uninspiring degree. Enough cut out for a "Rhadamanthine institution in this age and in these lands of the triumphant Cheap and Vulgar." Nothing vague or ambiguous or non-committal interests appeals in the least. We can do nothing without exasperation. We need that wholesomely stern state of the spirit before we need Money, which seems so dreadfully easy to come by. Regarding potential candidates, Owen Wister and Frank Millet. Thanks further for information about the new American copyright arrangements, although they help, at the same time they are not graceful. #6251-as
    - Henry James to Alvin [Langdon Coburn], 1909 May 21, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 6:60)
      Has been in town one week and left instructions for pile of volumes to be sent him once he is settled. Tell him which ones are missing, and he will supply them. Will come out and see him. Hopes confusions are subsidizing, and satisfaction great in his new home. #6251-g
    - H[enry] J[ames] to Alvin [Langdon Coburn], [1909] May 24, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 6:61)
      Will put off visit until everything conspires to captivate, as it will. Rest of volumes will have come by then, direct from Lamb House. #6251-g
    - Henry James to [Elizabeth] Jordan, 1909 June 2, typed transcript, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 6:62)
      He has thought about her invitation to contribute 3,000 words on the question of A Future Life to a symposium in Bazaar this summer. He will be glad to send paper by August 1, but doesn't think he does himself or his situation justice by assenting to $200. If she will make fee $300, he will proceed with matter. P.S. Should likely make it 4,000 words. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Hendrik [Christian Anderson], 1909 June 3, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 6:63)
      Rejoices in his health, his work, and in everything that is his. Hasn't had a very brilliant winter or spring, but he is 99 years old, but in better form now than for many months. In London 3 weeks, but home soon. Yearns over his Roman beauty and wishes he could be with him. The grand, green bronze, beautifully placed in his dining room niche, looks down upon him three times a day with his kindness and spirit rather than with any character of James's in its fine, blank green eyes. #6251
    - Henry James to Alvin [Langdon Coburn], 1909 June 17, ANS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 6:64)
      Will come Monday at 5 with pleasure, to see array of his treasures of every description. #6251-g
    - Henry James to Aline Harland, 1909 June 21, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 6:65)
      Has been beneath the wave of the London deluge and has been to Cambridge for May Week. Wonders if she would lunch with him at [Premier's?], Piccadilly, or tea, but lunch will grant more gratifying talk to her faithful old friend. #6251-y
    - Henry James to [Elizabeth] Jordon, 1909 July 8, typed transcript, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 6:66)
      Hears with pleasure her proposal for Immortality, his contribution to Bazaar will be $300. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Humphrey] Ward, 1909 July 11, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 6:67)
      Appreciates her sympathetic letter. The article in the Times Literary Supplement on his American editions by Percy Lubbock is a beautiful and intelligent thing, and it gives the greatest pleasure. It does that young man great honour, but it does him no less. It is soon for him to give way to elation at sixty six! But it does seem to suggest that's the more or less interpretive critic; let them hope that may be verified. Expects a relationless year, so he hopes to see her. Understruck at all her magnificent activity. Accepted his own similitude to the lumbering tortoise, and is trying to practice the motions of that animal on the stage of the Haymarket and elsewhere. #6251-a
    - Henry James to [Mrs. Daniel Sargent Curtis], 1909 July 17, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. with typed transcript. (Box-folder 6:68)
      He must have seemed absent and silent since their arrival in England: June and July days fill themselves more and more in the country, not less than in London, with complications, etc. He simply fled from London. Now back. Glad they are to be in York, even at price of motoring which he hates when he sees, hears, or smells it. Cars show the land and the world as nothing else does, and he is grateful they have come before he passed away. Great thing is they will be in England for some weeks, and he will come up to meet them in town. Discusses Dedham Church window and the murder of Sir. C. Wyllie who deserved such treachery as little as a man could. Thanks for her allusions to Percy Tublock's article in the Times Literary Supplement, which he found charming, and the most appreciative and fine tribute he has ever received. No leaving England for him this autumn. #6251-ag
    - Henry James to Hendrik [Christian Anderson], 1909 August 3, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 6:69)